Stanford University.
Let's just review for a moment the
the the chemistry that went into the
discovery of spin and um
fermionic character of
electrons, basically. The fermionic
character character implies two things.
And they're actually believed to be
related to each other, but they're
different.
One of them has to do with the spin of
the electron.
The spin of the electron is half spin.
And uh that means that the spin as far
as the spin goes, if we forget about the
orbital motion of the electron and so
forth,
the electron has two spin states
corresponding to spin a half, plus a
half and minus a half.
Uh
The other
property
that qualifies the electron as a fermion
is that
it satisfies the Pauli exclusion
principle. You can't put more than two
of them into the same state.
In talking about the states, spin
counts.
So, if for example
uh we ignored the spin
and for example, we talked about putting
two electrons into the ground state wave
function of a hydrogen atom,
yes, you can do that.
You can put two electrons into the
lowest energy level, but only because
you have the spin to soak up the uh the
Pauli exclusion principle.
And so, you put them in with opposite
spin. If you try to put a third one in,
you can't put it into the ground state.
You try to put a third one in,
let's say because we're dealing with
lithium.
It's uh of course for helium, we can put
both electrons into the ground state.
Uh in the approximation that we ignore
the interactions between the electrons.
In other words, in the chemist's bad
approximation, incidentally,
these days chemists are very
sophisticated quantum physicists really
good chemists and they're very
sophisticated.
But, you know, the old the old picture
of the atom, the shell model and all
those sorts of things that were
simplistic, which didn't work very well,
but you know, they work a little bit.
You can put two electrons into the
ground state of the helium atom. So, the
helium atom behaves as if you had two
electrons
both in lowest energy state.
Uh and that's okay because they have
opposite spins. If one is up, then the
other's down. If one is down, the other
is up.
In fact, those two electrons are
entangled.
They're entangled in exactly the way
that
uh well, they're entangled. One is up,
the other's down. One is down, the other
is up. And that's that's an entangled
state.
Uh once you go to lithium,
you can't put another electron into the
ground state. And I don't mean into the
ground state of the hydrogen of the
helium atom. I mean, of course, into the
ground state
of the electron wave functions in the
vicinity of the of the lithium nucleus.
Uh the lithium nucleus also has a
collect charge and it also has a
collection of wave functions for
electrons.
You can put the first one into the
ground state. You can put the second one
into ground state, but then the third
one has to go into another state. Simply
no room for it. By room, I mean from the
point of view of the exclusion
principle.
So, you start filling another shell.
And how many
how many energy levels are there at the
next shell? Well, we can draw our energy
level picture that we drew before.
Uh
Angular momentum zero, which is called
the S wave, at least for the simple
approximation in which the electrons
don't interact, there's the ground
state.
And then there are excited states, which
still have angular momentum zero
and so forth and so on.
And then
there's the P waves. The P waves are
angular momentum one or orbital angular
momentum one.
P stands for something, I don't know
what. And the first P wave has more
energy than the first S wave and it has
three states.
The three possible states of orbital
angular momentum one.
And then there are above that.
And by accident, by the accidents or the
they're not really accidents, of course,
but by the funny mathematics of the
Coulomb potential,
the first ex- the
Well, there's degeneracies, extra
degeneracies that I've indicated here on
the diagram. And so forth and so on.
S P D, that's spectroscopic notation. At
the next level,
the first sorry, at the next angular
momentum, this is L equals
zero, L equals one, L equals two.
At the next
at the at the D wave level, L equals
two, the lowest energy state is already
up to here.
One, two, three, four, five.
One, two, three, four, five and so
forth, five states for L equals two.
And that's what the pattern of energy
levels looks like.
Okay, so you go to the
you go to the
lithium atom.
The lithium atom, you put in two
electrons into the lowest energy state.
So, they're both in the lowest energy S
wave state. And now you have an extra
electron you have to do something with.
Well, you could put the extra electron
upstairs at some higher energy state,
but it would be unstable because it
would decay by emission of a photon,
which we haven't gotten to, but they
would but it would decay down to
something of lower energy.
What you can do is put the next electron
into any one of
these four
states.
Okay?
Keep going. What comes after lithium? I
can't remember.
Beryllium.
Okay, then you come to beryllium.
Beryllium, you fill the lowest one and
you fill one of the next levels. But
wait a minute, there's four electrons
now.
So, you fill two of them.
Okay.
That's uh beryllium. What comes after
beryllium?
Boron? Boron.
Boron, okay. And the one after boron?
Carbon.
Who? Carbon. Carbon, good.
Right.
And if there wasn't spin, at the next
level, which would at the next atom,
which is
What's the next one? Hm? What is it?
Nitrogen. Nitrogen. At the next nitrogen
level, you would have to start filling
up these up here. But that's not the way
it works. The spectroscopy
and everything we know about it is
consistent with putting
the fifth is it the fifth electron?
One,
two,
whatever. Uh the uh the uh
the next one
fits in again into one of these levels.
And that works until you've gotten to
neon? Neon. Neon.
Okay.
In neon, there are eight electrons in
this first excited energy level here.
Why are there eight? Well, one for each
orbital angular one for each orbital
state, but
up but you also have the spin degree of
freedom. So, there are eight states that
can be occupied here. And then beyond
neon, I I don't remember my chemistry,
whatever. Sodium.
Who? Sodium.
Sodium? Yeah.
Right. Sodium is the next metal.
And uh right, you have to put one of
them up here.
And you know the story. I mean, you know
the story as well as I do.
Uh valence electrons and so forth.
Uh
Sodium looks sort of like hydrogen and
so does lithium because it has one extra
electron in a
outer in the outermost
uh electron orbit and so forth. I didn't
want to do chemistry tonight.
I just wanted to remind you
that two things seem to go together,
the exclusion principle and the spin a
half.
Now, could you have Here's an
interesting question. Could you have
particles
which were spin a half, but didn't have
an exclusion principle?
You could put that spin a half.
Oh,
before I talk about that, let's talk
about photons.
Do photons have an exclusion principle?
Photons most certainly do not have an
exclusion principle.
And in fact, classical electromagnetic
waves are typically waves in which many
many many quanta, photons, are all in
the same state.
That's what makes them classical, that
they have a very very large amplitude, a
very very large number of photons all in
the same state.
And so, photons most certainly don't
have an exclusion principle.
In fact, it's almost the opposite.
There's a tendency for them to want to
be in the same state, but of course
photons don't want anything.
But they do tend to congregate into the
same state.
Whereas fermions
the half spin particles can't be in the
same state.
So you might ask, could there be a
particle of half spin
which doesn't satisfy the Pauli
exclusion principle?
Or could there be a particle of integer
spin? Photon is an integer spin
particle, spin one.
Or even spin zero.
Could there be one of those which does
satisfy the Pauli exclusion principle?
And the interesting fact is that they go
together.
Half integer spin, that doesn't
necessarily mean spin one half. It could
be spin three halves, spin five halves,
spin seven halves.
Uh those half spin objects
always
satisfy the exclusion principle.
And and the spin integer particles never
satisfy the exclusion principle. Is that
a theoretical result?
That's a theoretical result.
From something more fundamental?
Uh
it can be derived from the principles of
quantum field theory. We won't get to
that. But I'll show you a little
demonstration
tonight. All you need is a belt
to understand some aspects of it.
There's some interesting topological
aspects of it which we'll try to get to.
This is
Yeah, it's not a theorem in
non-relativistic quantum mechanics. No,
it's not. And
That's correct. That's correct. It's not
a theorem. And it's also not true in one
or two dimensions, spatial dimensions.
Right.
That's true.
For the bosonic states, is there a
maximum number of quanta you can put
into a given state? In the bosonic case?
No.
And there's a strong tendency for them
to want to get into the same state.
Okay. And we'll try to get to that.
All right, this business is a tale of
two minus signs.
Two distinct different minus signs.
Uh one having to do with spin and one
having to do with
what I'll call exchange. But before I
talk Well, before we
talk a little more about the
relationship between the half spin and
the exclusion principle,
let's talk about
the Pauli exclusion principle itself,
which um
has a deeper meaning than just saying
you can't put two particles into the
same state.
It's a statement about the nature of
wave functions of multi-particle
systems.
If I have a multi-particle system, and
now when I say wave functions, let's for
the moment forget the spin, and I'll
come back to the spin and tell you what
to do about it, but uh
but let's forget about spin for a moment
and say that the coordinates of the
particles
that we're talking about are called
X sub I. I does not stand for X, Y, and
Z. It stands for particle one, particle
two, particle three, and so forth.
So X1 represents particle one, and so
forth.
And um
X could be X, Y, or Z.
We're going to We're going to suppress
the the three components of position.
Just call them X.
But I represents the particle.
And then the um a
basis of state vectors
is to give the positions
of all of the particles.
Let's write X1, X2, X3.
Just as for one particle, we can label a
complete set of states by just
prescribing the position of the
particle,
for a system of particles, we can just
label all of the positions, and those
are an orthonormal family of states, a
complete set of states.
And just as for one particle, we can
define the wave function
to be the inner product whatever the
state vector happens to be. This is an
abstract state.
It's an abstract state of the system of
N particles, some number of particles.
And the wave function itself
is the inner product of the state vector
with the specific state vectors.
Let's call it XN.
That is called
psi of
X1 through XN.
What do you do with it?
You square it. Well, you don't square
it. You multiply it by its complex
conjugate.
And when you multiplied it by its
complex conjugate, the result is a
probability. It's the probability to
find the first particle at X1, the
second particle at X2, the third
particle at X3, and so forth.
So this is multi-particle quantum
mechanics in a nutshell.
Now, let's suppose that what we're
talking about is identical particles. In
other words, particles of exactly the
same species.
Electrons or whatever they happen to be.
Ignoring spin for the moment.
Uh
particles which are identical, we have
to ask the question. We talked about it
last time.
Uh we have to ask the question
of
whether
a
part particle one at position one and
particle two at position two, is it the
same state or is it a different state
than particle two at position one and
particle one at position two.
In other words,
that's the blue electron at part at
position X1. That's the red electron at
position two. But electrons don't have
colors.
They're identical, indistinguishable.
And so it's an interesting question to
ask, is this should this state
be counted as exactly the same as
the state
with a red electron at X1 and a blue
electron at X2?
As far as we know from all experiments
as well as from all theory, from quantum
field theory, relativistic quantum
mechanics,
the rule is that these are the same
state.
So for example, let's just take two
particles.
That tells us for example that
the state that I would label X1 X2,
blue particle at position X1, red
particle at position X2, is exactly the
same as
red particle at position X2. Sorry.
Blue. Which one was number one?
Number one is blue.
Blue particle at X2, red particle at X1.
In other words,
there is no difference
between
a state
where the part
two particles are two particles, to say
it that way.
On the other hand, in quantum mechanics,
um the physics of a state, the physical
properties of a state,
physical properties of a state,
don't depend on one particular
parameter. They don't depend on the
overall phase in front of the state
vector.
In terms of wave functions, the overall
phase in front of the wave function
never plays into anything that is
physically measurable.
That's because all probabilities and all
expectation values involve psi times psi
star. So it's conceivable
that really the right relationship is
not that X1 X2 is equal to X2 X1,
but something a little bit looser than
that. X1 X2 is a phase, E to the I phi.
Uh some numerical number
which is a pure phase.
Let's write it E to the I phi of some So
a phi is just a fixed number.
It's possible that when you interchange
two particles,
that the wave function
should pick up a phase.
On the other hand, supposing you do it
twice.
Supposing you interchange X1 and X2,
and you say when I interchange X1 and
X2,
the wave function should get multiplied
by the phase E to the I phi, and then
you do it again. You interchange them
again. You get back to the same place.
You get back to the same place. You get
back to the same state that you started
with.
Uh
in other words, when you interchange
twice, you really do have to come back
to the same thing. There's no other no
other possibility.
So the general guess would be
that E to the I phi here is either plus
or minus one.
It's an operation. When you do it twice,
you get one.
But
there are two possibilities. There are
two
sensible possibilities. Well, you might
say only one sensible possibility, but
then you'd be leaving out half the
particles in the world.
equals plus
Those are called bosons.
Particles which satisfy that property
that when you interchange any two of
them
and in fact it could be a multi-particle
state where you just take any two and
interchange them
if the state is exactly the same
then they're called bosons. So, bosons
satisfy the property that the wave
function or the state vector when you
interchange any two of them stays the
same.
Fermions are the case with the minus
sign.
Okay, so when you switch two fermions
identical fermions
the state vector
changes sign. Keeping in mind that the
change of sign is itself not observable.
It's not an observable thing because the
probability distributions, expectation
values, everything of interest
uh involves psi times psi star. All
right, so
if the state vectors change in this way
then the same must be true of the wave
functions. For example
let's take X1 X2
psi
That's by definition psi of X1 and X2.
Whoops. That's a bit
the wave function of particle one and
part and particle two.
The other hand
is X2 X1.
That's equal
to psi of X2 X1.
In other words
the two wave functions
are related to each other by just by
switching the arguments.
But now, if the state vectors themselves
have this property that they either
change sign or don't change sign, then
the wave functions must have the same
property. So, this becomes a property of
wave functions.
And let's write it down.
If you have a wave function for
fermions, for a system of fermions, X1
and now let's
well, let's just do it for two particles
and then I'll tell you what to do for
many particles.
The rule is for fermions it must be
equal
to minus what you would get if you
interchange the particles.
You interchange the particles, the wave
function changes sign for fermions.
What about bosons? For bosons
no change of sign.
X1 X2
equals plus
Okay, let's uh let's think about some
states and see what what sense we can
make out of this.
Supposing I have let's take the case of
bosons first. The case of bosons is a
little simpler.
No sign no change of sign. Let's suppose
we have two bosons
in two different states.
Well, one state could be
let's again forgetting spin.
One state could correspond to some
particular wave It doesn't have to be an
atom incidentally. It could just be any
system.
Uh but let's let's take some of these
atomic states here.
Okay.
This wave function or the wave function
associated with this state here could be
called psi zero, let's call it. Zero
because it has zero angular momentum and
because it's the lowest energy state.
All right, so we're going to put
particle one into that state.
So, the wave function
for particle one would be psi zero of
X1.
Let's put the next particle in some
other state. It could be It could have
the same angular momentum or a different
angular momentum. Uh but let's make it a
different state.
Let's make it a different state.
Oh.
Let's first do the case where we put two
particles into the same state.
Oh.
Let's put two particles into the same
state.
Then
the state vector would be psi zero of
X2.
Particle one in the state psi zero,
particle two in the state psi zero.
Does this satisfy the rule for fermions?
Does it satisfy the rule for bosons?
Well
this structure here is obviously
unchanged if you interchange one and
two.
It doesn't matter which order you
multiply wave functions.
Wave functions are just have numerical
values. They're not operators. They
commute.
Okay, so
this wave function here
two particles in the same state
that's symmetric. The word is symmetric.
Symmetric on the interchange of the two
arguments of the wave function. It does
not change sign.
So, that if such a wave function makes
any sense
it makes sense only for bosons.
Okay.
For fermions, this is not possible
because this does not satisfy the rule
for fermions.
Okay, let's try another state.
Okay, this
And another way of saying it is you can
you can only put bosons into the same
state. Two bosons into the same state.
Okay, let's take one particle and put it
into psi zero and the other particle put
it into another state which I'll call
psi one.
Okay.
What happens if I interchange one and
two?
Uh
not zero and one, but what happens if I
interchange X1 and X2?
This will become
psi zero of X2
psi one of X1.
In general, if these are two different
wave functions
the left side and the right side will
neither be equal to each other nor equal
to their
negative.
Just the just product of two functions.
Sine of X1 times hyperbolic moose of uh
of X2.
Okay. That has no symmetry whatever.
It doesn't change sign or it doesn't
stay the same. So, this is not a
possible wave function for either
fermions or bosons. Does that mean you
can't put one particle into one state
and another particle into another state?
Not quite.
Let me make a Let me now
take a state
which is made by taking both of these
combinations here and adding them.
This is a wave function, perfectly good
wave function.
It's a superposition of particle one
being in psi zero, particle two being in
psi one, and the opposite. Particle two
being in psi but both of them have a
particle
in psi zero and a particle in psi one.
They both satisfy the criteria that
there's a particle in psi one and a
particle in psi two.
So, both states have been filled.
But what about this? What happens to
this if I interchange one and two?
Nothing. Nothing. It stays the same.
Okay? So, this is a perfectly good
candidate for a boson system. Two
particles in the same No.
A particle in state one uh oops, in
state zero and a particle in state one.
And here's how you build it.
What about fermions? Can you build Can
you create a state
with a fermion
in this state
in this state?
Yes. All you have to do is put a minus
sign here.
Okay, can you check? Does that change
sign when you interchange X1 and X2?
Sure, it does.
This one goes over to here. This one
goes over to here. And the whole thing
just changes sign.
So, yes, you can put In both cases
you can put a particle into state one
and a particle into state zero.
What you can't do for fermions is put
two particles in the same state
and two particles or for bosons you can.
Okay. In particular
let's take the special case of exactly
this
where psi one and psi zero are the same
state. It's just a special case in which
instead of taking two different states
I take the same state.
Okay? So, two possibilities
psi zero of X1 psi one of X2
plus
psi zero of X two
psi one of X1.
Boson
fermion wave function.
Now, let's take the case as I said where
both wave functions are the same.
Well, this just gives me twice the
original wave function.
All right, it may not be normalized
correctly. We may have to normalize it
appropriately, but it gives us twice the
original wave function and it's not
zero. Nothing wrong with it. Again, it's
two bosons in the same state. Perfectly
good.
But, the fermionic construction here
gives us what?
Zero.
So, again, we can't make a state in
which two fermions are in the same
state.
The same rule continues if you have
multi-particle states.
If you have multi-particle states, any
number of particles, then the wave
function is a function of many
variables.
And it has the property
that for bosons, if you take any two of
them
and switch them,
the wave function does not change sign.
For fermions, if you take any two of
them and switch them, it does change
sign. Again, what happens if you switch
twice, so that you come back to the same
configuration?
Clearly, in both cases, nothing happens.
Right.
So, the process of
double swap
is no is nothing at all. It's trivial.
It doesn't do anything, as you would
expect. As you would expect. Uh but, the
odd thing is that the process of single
swap, which you might have thought does
nothing,
changes the sign of the wave function
for fermions.
Okay, so that's that's
if you like, the
basis, the mathematical
basis, the mathematical um
set of rules that goes with the Pauli
exclusion principle. Like, you can't put
two particles into the same state for
fermions.
Now, what about when there's spin?
Well, when there's spin, the easiest way
to think about it
is just to add another, for each
particle, instead of saying the wave
function is only a function of
position,
think of it as a function of position
and spin.
All right.
So, in that way, you can think of the
wave function
as a function of position
and, let's say, whether it's up or down.
We could choose sigma Z here.
Z component of spin.
This wave function has the following
meaning.
It's square
Sorry, it it's magnitude, it's squared
magnitude is the probability to find the
particle at position X
with spin either up or down, depending
on whether you put in sigma Z equals one
or sigma Z equals minus one.
So, it's a function of a continuous
variable and a discrete variable, plus
or minus one.
And it represents the amplitude, the
probability amplitude for the particle
to have a certain location with a spin
either up or down.
Once you know that, then you say, "Okay,
the wave function for many particles
One here stands for the particle, not
whether it's X, Y, or Z.
X2
sigma 2, and so forth and so on.
This representing the wave function
for a particle to be at position one
with spin sigma one, position two with
spin sigma two, and so forth and so on.
And the rule is exactly the same
that if you take
all of the all of the stuff
that's associated with particle one,
that's both X and sigma,
and you take
the things which are associated with
particle two and switch them,
for bosons, nothing happens. For
fermions, the spin change Sorry, the the
sign changes.
All right, but what it boils down to
is exactly what we said in the first
place. You simply can't put two
particles into the same state, including
spin.
Including the spin if they're fermions,
you can if they're bosons.
Okay, any questions about that so far?
Yeah.
Um
You know what this sort of reminds me of
a little bit is is that you've got a
bunch of things and you
kind of interchange them for fermions
and you get a minus sign. So, this makes
me think about the the the permute you
know, the the minus sign
for permutations. This is this These are
the representations of the permutation
group. Okay, so this so that comes into
this.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah, switching the
particles is a permutation.
And what happens to them under
permutation, a plus or minus sign,
defines a representation of the
permutation group.
Right, this is very definitely has to do
with permutations. So,
it not only reminds you of it, it is it.
When you wrote down when you had
particle one in psi zero and particle
two in psi one, you wrote that as the
product. Why not the sum?
Oh, no, the sum The sum of two wave
functions for one
is a wave function for one particle.
It's simply the superposition of
um
To build a theory of two particles,
the state vectors are the tensor
products.
Are in a tensor product space
of the
of the wave functions that depend on two
variables.
And uh no, you wouldn't want to add
them. Adding them would correspond to
putting a single particle into a
superposition of states. Right.
Yeah.
So, right, there's two things you can do
if you have two wave functions.
You can take a single particle and put
it in the sum of the two of them, or you
can take two particles and put one in
one and one in the other. And for one in
one and one in the other, the rule would
be the product. Yeah.
So, um here we have uh two particles and
swapping the particles gives
interference effects. Gives what?
Interference effects.
Well, so far we So far I haven't I
It It certainly does give interference
effects, but uh
uh
we haven't talked about interference
yet. I may talk about a little bit about
interference later and the effects of
these things. Well, the fact that you
you got zero when you
calculated that means that the amplitude
squared is going to be zero. So, there's
no probability for it to be like that,
which is
destructive in effect. Indeed.
You That's right. You could say the
Pauli exclusion All right, fine. You
could say the Pauli exclusion principle
is a manifestation of a funny kind of
interference
where
if you put the two particles in the same
state,
they and switch them,
they interfere. Good. So, yes, so it is
a kind of interference phenomenon.
You're right.
Yeah.
Is it just the same logic
Pauli used to derive the exclusion
principle?
Yes.
Yeah.
Um
Of course, when Pauli was doing it, he
wasn't deriving the
principle.
It was an empirical fact. And he was, if
you like, interpreting the principle,
finding a mathematical framework in
which the principle uh
would be correct.
Later on, of course, once uh there was a
relativistic theory of particles and uh
this rule here became part of the logic,
inescapable logic, then there was a
derivation of the of the equivalence
principle. Uh
the exclusion principle.
So, he was just trying to describe an
empirical fact? He was trying at first
to describe an empirical fact. Of
course, once he realized this,
that there was such a nice mathematics
to it, undoubtedly, he started looking
for deeper reasons for the mathematics.
And eventually, he found them. He and uh
Dirac and uh
He and Dirac and
He, Dirac, and Einstein were the uh were
the um
uh
the people who really
built this. And Bose, but uh
and Fermi, I suppose. I don't know if
you know, for the life of me, I
Fermi was a very, very great physicist
who did very thing. Excuse me, Giorgio,
I don't want to insult the Italians, but
uh there he is.
Uh
But, um but I really don't understand
what he had to do with any of this.
Okay.
Um
Giorgio, your homework is to find out
what Fermi
So, um for a single particle,
essentially, swapping two
indistinguishable paths gives
interference.
Is there some connection between those
two things?
Between what and what? Uh between
swapping particles giving interference
and swapping paths giving interference.
Well, what you're doing is you're Yeah,
um
You have two paths for two particles.
This path where one goes this way, one
goes this way, and another path where
they cross over. They sort of wind up
the same way.
And with bosons, they add. With
fermions, they they can cancel. So, it's
it's it's it is connected with
interference, but I I I didn't want to
do that now. There is an interesting
interference experiment that you can do.
Um but let's let's come to it later.
Okay, that's the tail. That's That's one
minus sign.
Now, uh this sign will come back at us
many many times,
but there's another minus sign
that has to do not with
exchange. This is the minus sign that
has to do with exchange of particles.
This is the minus sign that has to do
with spin,
but it has to do with rotation about an
axis by 2 pi.
Rotation by 2 pi is another process
that you might expect does nothing.
Right?
You might expect rotation by 2 pi
is a mathematical process that you can
my imagine in your head, but if you take
a system and imagine mathematically
rotating it by 2 pi, not not grabbing it
and rotating it, but mathematically just
performing a transformation
which rotates it by 2 pi. You've done
nothing to it.
You've done nothing to it because a
rotation by 2 pi
is just the identity rotation. It's the
same as the identity rotation.
You think.
Or I thought.
You may not think. I did think I did
think at one time in my life.
So, you might say, "Okay, let's now
consider a wave function for a particle,
one particle now."
Psi of X.
And now let's rotate our frame of
reference.
Or better yet, rotate the particle.
I'm all I'm interested I'm only
interested in the spin right now.
But uh but the
All right, so there's a wave function of
the particle. It might depend both on
position and spins. Yeah, so we can we
can put some spin in here.
It depends on
whatever it depends on, but in
particular it depends on the spin.
And now we rotate by some angle.
What happens when you rotate a state
with a given angular momentum
by an angle?
Well,
you have an idea?
Um are we rotating this about the
About any axis whatever. An exterior
axis. An exterior axis. Right, an
exterior axis. The particle could be
located The particle could be located at
the origin. So, this is essentially
orbital
angular momentum
No, it's whatever angular momentum it
has. Everything. Everything. Right.
Uh
Everything, including the spin rotation
and so forth. Do we orient with respect
to the spin?
In your rotation We don't know what the
spin is. The spin No, no, it it
It could be Yes, it could be rotation
about the Z axis.
Remember, the spin doesn't have to be
along the spin Z axis. It could be along
the X axis, could be along Y axis, could
be along any axis. So, the axis of its
angular momentum could be located.
Yes. If it's angular momentum is
pointing in some direction and you
rotate about some other axis, the
angular momentum could rotate about that
axis. But,
by the time
Here's the angular momentum. Here's the
axis we're rotating about.
And we rotate. But by the time we come
back by 2 pi, we come back to the same
place.
So, you might expect
that if you rotate the wave function
Remember, rotations are unitary
transformations. Let's just call it R. R
for rotation. We rotate the wave
function by an angle theta.
We rotate the wave function by an angle
of theta, we get something new in
general, but if we rotate by 2 pi,
then presumably we should get the same
thing back.
The probability should be unchanged. The
probability for spin should be
unchanged. The probability for anything
should be unchanged because all we did
was an imaginary process where we in our
heads rotated about 2 pi.
Uh
And so we should come back to the same
thing.
But wait.
The same issue occurs as occurred over
here for exchanging particles.
If all we require is that probabilities
and expectation values don't change,
then it's possible that when you rotate
by 2 pi,
uh you pick up a phase.
Again, could be a plus or minus one.
Um
it could be a plus or minus one.
It might even be some weird phase,
but
there's the possibility that a phase
could be in here.
Now, how does the phase that occurs
there
depend on the angular momentum of the
state, the total angular momentum of the
state? The angular momentum Remember
what the angular momentum is. The
angular momentum, let's write the total
angular momentum now that includes the
spin and the orbital angular momentum.
It's usually called J.
J is the generator of rotations.
That means when it acts on a state,
when J acts on a state,
it sort of differentiates it with
respect to an angle.
In particular, let's say J, the Z
component of J, the Z component of the
angular momentum.
That effectively takes the state
and just like momentum differentiates a
state with respect to position, angular
momentum differentiates it with respect
to angle.
So,
let's write that out. That's in fact
correct. Minus I
the derivative of the state
with respect to some rotation angle.
If we imagine rotating the state by a
little bit or any amount, then acting
with J
does the same thing as differentiating
with respect to theta.
That's what a momentum does. That's what
an angular momentum does with respect to
an angle. And this angle would now would
be about the Z axis.
We're rotating about the Z axis and
that's generated by the generator JZ.
Okay.
Um
Let's suppose
that the angular momentum about the Z
axis had a definite value.
The eigen value equation.
Then we would write that this is equal
to M. M would be the eigen value of JZ.
It would just be M times psi. Oops.
M times psi.
We can think of this We can think of psi
as a function or as a vector. It doesn't
matter. What's the solution of this
equation?
The solution
is that psi of theta.
In other words, the psi that you get
when you rotate by angle theta is what?
E to the I M theta
psi of zero.
This is just the equation that says a
derivative of something is equal to M
times the something.
And that would be the solution of it.
Okay.
Remember what what were the eigen values
that we discovered were possible
for the Z component of angular momentum
when we analyzed the commutation
relations?
Remember we did that? We found two kinds
of things.
One had integer spectrum and the other
had half integer spectrum.
That was just a mathematical exercise
using the commutation relations, just
abstract algebra,
and just fiddling with it, following
Dirac, following Dirac as far as as
Dirac followed his nose, just uh
playing with commutators, we found out
that M
could only be integers or half integers.
What if M is a half integer and you
rotate by 2 pi?
In other words, supposing you rotate all
the ways around the axis, so that theta
is 2 pi,
then
we get the fact that E to the I 2 pi M
times psi again.
E to the 2 pi M is one if M is an
integer,
but it's minus one if M is a half
integer.
So, evidently, these representations or
these multiplets
that have half integer spin have the odd
property that when you rotate around by
2 pi,
the wave function changes sign.
Those are the only two possibilities.
The spectrum is either integer spin or
half integer spin. It's true in two
dimensions, it's different.
But, in three dimensions,
uh the spin
is either the integer type or the
half-integer type,
which means that when you rotate around
a full 2 pi, either the wave function
changes sign or it doesn't.
Uh
whether it changes sign or it doesn't
simply depends on what kind of particle
you're talking about.
Incidentally, if you rotate by 4 pi,
it comes back to itself.
4 pi is 2 pi squared. No, 4 pi is 2 pi.
You know what I mean.
Yeah. Now, there's a demonstration that
goes with this, which really does
reflect some of the mathematics.
In the mathematics, it seems that
rotating by 2 pi is not the identity for
fermions.
It's not the identity.
It doesn't change expectation values. It
doesn't change
uh uh
probabilities, but it is not the
identity operation. A little while
tonight, I'll show you how actually the
ro- the rotation by 2 pi is an
observable effect.
It is an observable effect, and
therefore, I think we have to say
that in quantum mechanics, rotation by 2
pi is not the same as no rotation at
all.
There's something going on in the
mathematics of rotations,
which says you have to rotate by 4 pi
for the mathematical operator
to give you just one.
All right. Now, there's a famous trick.
I believe it was done due to my friend
uh
I don't know who first invented it.
It was Dirac who certainly first
invented it
who uh understood it. But, long after
Dirac,
a uh circus performer by the name of
Gerardus 't Hooft was a
uh a Dutch circus performer
invented a trick to demonstrate the fact
that rotations by 2 pi are not the
identity, and rotations by 4 pi are the
identity. I love to do this so much
that I'm going to do it, and you're
supposed to do it with a cup of coffee.
All right. So, here's here's the trick.
Here's this. I'm going to rotate by 2
pi. Okay, now don't worry. I'm not going
to go rotate this way.
I'm going to rotate this way.
Okay? That is not the identity. Let me
tell you, I'm quite certain that's not
the identity. Let me rotate another 2
pi.
That's the identity.
Now, there is mathematics to that.
Gerard
I I think he did discover it. Now, what
uh what I think Dirac understood was a
little bit different. Oh, it was the
same thing.
I think his picture was you take a
sphere, and you put it in a box.
And you connect the sphere by ropes. You
know,
um
Here's your sphere. Here's your box.
And you have ropes connecting it now,
strings connecting it to the box in in
all possible directions. Okay?
First thing two-dimensionally,
what happens if you rotate the ball by 2
pi?
You get a tangle, right?
You get a tangle.
You can't undo that tangle.
Rotate by 4 pi, you still can't undo it
in in uh in two dimensions.
In three dimensions, what is true
is if you rotate by 2 pi, you get a
tangle. That tangle is basically the
tangle of my arm uh after I go 2 pi.
But, then if you rotate again
4 pi, you can untangle.
So, this is a theorem. It's a theorem
about uh of the topology of the rotation
group. It's a theorem that no matter how
complicated the set of connections
with the walls of the box, if you rotate
by pi, 2 pi, sorry, you cannot disengage
the strings back to the original
configuration. If you rotate by 4 pi,
you can.
So, it really is a mathematical
fact about rotations
that rotations do not bring you back to
the same configuration after
uh rotate by 2 pi, unless you
specifically say, "I'm only going to
study the kind of wave functions which
do come back."
Then you're dealing with bosons,
and the other possibility is the kind of
wave functions that change sign.
But, if you
with the with the sphere and the
connected strings, rotating twice twice
around the same axis, Yeah. you can
untangle. Yeah.
I just showed you. Wait, but it looked
like you a little different like you
were working in the fourth dimension or
something.
No, no, third dimension.
It looked like you were working in an
extra dimension.
Yeah, but
well, you're also working in an extra
dimension here. It's time. You're you
know, you're rotating it with time, but
uh but that's not the point. Yeah, you
are in a sense working in a
you're following a path in the in the
space of rotations.
And a path in the space of rotations can
be unwound for 4 pi. It can't be unwound
for 2 pi.
So, it's a it's and um
you know, any topologist will recognize
this as a uh feature of
uh of um
uh
Okay, so that is the difference between
the half-spin rep- rota- uh
representations and the integer spin
representations,
their behavior under 2 pi rotations.
Fermions get a minus sign.
Bosons don't get a minus sign.
So, we have an interesting situation. As
I said, a tale of two minus signs.
Fermions, the wave function for two
fermions, now this is for two fermions,
changes sign when you swap them.
The wave function for a single fermion
changes sign when you rotate it by 2 pi.
Wouldn't it be interesting if there was
some mathematical connection
between rotation by 2 pi
and exchange? And there is such a
connection.
This even theoretical physicists
tend not to know this for some reason. I
don't know why.
Mathematicians were stunned by it when I
showed them. They didn't know it.
Most theoretical physicists don't know
it.
It was a discovery of a friend of mine
by the name of David Finkelstein, who
was uh one of the unsung heroes of
physics.
Uh he's a
he
whether he's a famous physicist or not
depends on who on what uh what crowd of
people you're asking.
If you're asking an older generation of
very, very famous physicists, like Roger
Penrose and people like that, they
certainly know who David Finkelstein was
is.
If you ask the man in the street, they
never heard of David Finkelstein. They
say, "My butcher was named David
Finkelstein, my butcher in the Bronx."
But, David Finkelstein was one of the
great unsung heroes of theoretical
physics. He figured this out. I'm going
to show you what he figured out. It's
really fascinating.
Uh
Here's my belt.
Now, I'm going to do something with the
belt, and then we're going to talk about
what it is I did. I hope I can do it. I
think I can do it.
All right, we're going to we're going to
do a double twist of my belt, okay?
A double
This is done easily with a rubber band,
but if I did it with a rubber band, you
couldn't see it from here. All right,
notice if I hold it this way,
you see an exchange.
You see
the two bottoms of the belt here having
a been exchanged.
On the other hand, if I turn it around,
you see there's a rotation by 2 pi.
The belt has been twisted by 2 pi.
Okay?
A rotation by 2 pi
together with an exchange gives you
nothing at all.
Gives you an untwisted belt.
So, somehow in the mathematics of I'll
draw the picture. I I think I can draw
what uh
the picture is.
Uh just in case you couldn't see it on
my belt. I'm just drawing what was going
on in my belt.
Let's see.
It looks something like this.
Um
Will I ever get to this if I uh
if I twist my belt?
I don't think so.
Okay, what do I have to do to to make it
a legal twist of my belt? What I have to
do
is twist it by 2 pi.
Then it's a legal twist of the belt.
That's what I showed you by twisting it,
and uh
that's a legal twist of the belt,
meaning to say, you can twist the belt
that way, and if you do, and you it
apart, you just get
the trivial the topologically trivial
belt
like that.
So, this is equivalent to this, and what
it's telling us
is
a deep topological connection between
the process of exchanging. If I have
This could be thought of in the
following way.
But if I have two particles
and I do two processes on them. The
first process is
I take one of them and rotate it by 2
pi.
And the other process Well,
and the other process is I switch two of
them.
They cancel each other out.
So, that means, quite apart from whether
they're fermions or bosons, I I I
appreciate this is not an obvious
uh connection. I'm telling you this
because a lot of people think this
really is at the root of the spin
statistics theorem. I do.
Um
that the deep topological connection
between rotation and exchange may very
well be what's going on.
Uh
and
what it says
is that whatever you
doing nothing
is like doing a rotation by 2 pi
and an exchange both together.
Okay, that that is uh
This is not the way Pauli proved the
spin spin statistics theorem.
Question. Yeah. Um
So, this one doesn't have anything to do
with the topology of the belt, but has
to do with the how the belt sits in
space, and it's in rotational space.
but particles sit in space, too, you
know.
Right. And time. This can be thought of
as a history with time going up.
This can be thought of as a history. If
you want to think of it as a history,
you imagine that a pair of particles was
created over here. You had no particles
and you created a pair.
Same thing over here. You had no
particles and you created a pair. So, by
the time you've
gotten to this level over here, you have
four particles. One, two,
three, four, right?
You have four particles, each
being thought of as um
as a cross-section through the belt.
Okay. Now, what you're doing is you're
taking one of the particles
and rotating it by 2 pi.
And at the same time, you're taking the
other two particles and switching them.
And what it's saying is the switching of
these two particles, whatever sign you
may or may not get,
must cancel the sign that you get for
rotating one of them.
Okay, this is this is something deep
that's never been completely explored.
Uh yeah. Is there is there
Is there a connection between this and
the idea of a
uh
Möbius strip where you
switch the two sides
the top of the
Yeah, it's connected with that.
It's connected with that.
Um
Right.
But a path, a process. A process
Yeah, well, okay. So, let's see what the
process is.
The process is you start with nothing.
You see, this kind of logic only makes
sense in a theory where particles can be
created.
It would not make sense in a theory
where
particles were eternal. Yes.
Uh I've seen another
funny argument
um about exchanging
going by 2 pi by
by having two particles
um basically taking a symmetric role in
the exchange.
And I didn't really like this argument,
but I wonder what you think of it. Mhm.
Okay? So, when we exchange them, one
goes one pi, the other goes the other
pi. But
we actually cause them to
spin.
Mhm. Okay? By pi. So, we need to rotate
them by pi in order to get the
identity back.
You rotate each one by pi.
Yeah, so we get 2 pi because there's
this one, and then there's this one, so
that's 2 pi.
And then you rotate
be the same mathematical fact. 180°
here, 180° there, and now they're both
pointing the same direction Mhm. if they
were pointing the same direction
opposite directions if they were
pointing opposite directions. Well, it's
a little bit different because what we
want to study is a rotation by 2 pi, not
two rotations by pi, but um that sounds
like they might be connected.
Um
Okay, what's the process that's
reflected here? You start with nothing.
Now, in a theory where particles can be
created out of nothing,
quantum field theory is a theory where
particles can be created.
But there are other kinds of theories
where particles can also be created.
Just uh creating certain kinds of
excitations in condensed matter physics
can create particles.
But in a theory where particles can be
created, you start with no particles.
So, your starting point is no particles.
A blank blackboard.
And then over here and over here,
basically you're you're creating a
particle and an antiparticle. Over here
and over here, you're creating a
particle and an antiparticle.
If these particles were charged
and you create them out of nothing,
obviously they must have opposite
charge,
but
that's not the important thing here.
You
do whatever it takes in your theory to
create a pair of particles out of
nothing.
You have to put in energy, for sure,
but you do it. And now you're left with
four particles. One, two,
three, four.
Let's see. Um
particle, antiparticle, particle,
antiparticle.
And then, with time, as time goes on,
at the same time that you rotate one of
these by 2 pi,
at the same time, you interchange these
two.
So, I suppose if this is a plus charge
and this is a minus charge, this better
be a minus charge and this better be a
plus charge because you're going to
interchange the two minus charges.
You get some phase
from rotating this particle, and you get
some phase from
interchanging these two. But as you can
see, topologically this is completely
equivalent to just creating a single
pair of particles and annihilating them,
and for that, there is no phase.
So,
whatever phase you got from exchanging
must cancel against the phase that you
got from rotation. I like this argument
a lot. I think this can be turned into a
real argument.
Uh
But I I've never actually seen it done.
So, uh it's a mean it's What's very
surprising is how few physicists
actually know this argument.
Um
Anyway, it does show It does show that
there is a connection between rotations
and
uh and exchanges.
And a real a relation of the right kind.
Okay?
So, that was the tail.
Does it show it or does it suggest it?
This is a suggestive argument that I've
never seen turned into a rigorous
argument.
Uh
It's the closest I can do to a proof of
the spin statistics theorem without
going through the complexities of You
see,
what
what some of us noticed a long time ago,
in the '60s and so forth, and that's
when David
did this.
Rather famous paper, but um
not famous enough.
What people noticed is that
the spin statistics was more general
than just relativistic Lorenzen variant
quantum field theory, which is what
Pauli proved it for.
You could prove it for all kinds of
particles that you could make things
called solitons or things called
solitary waves.
A solitary wave is just a lump.
A lump
uh a lump of field. A lump of field
that
doesn't have to be in a relativistic
field theory. Any kind of theory where
you can
manipulate the fields and create lumps.
This would apply to the lumps.
That was kind of noticed by a few
people, particularly Finkelstein and the
Rubenstein and
uh
a few others.
And it was Finkelstein who said, "Look,
that's the criteria that you can create
particles. If you can create and
annihilate particles, then they must
satisfy this rule, whether or not it's
relativistic quantum field theory."
So, that's why
it's even true for
uh lumps of stuff in condensed matter
physics. Certain kinds of particles
which are just excitations lumped that's
true for magnetic monopoles, it's true
for all kinds of things where Pauli's
argument really doesn't apply directly.
So, presumably this is what I what is at
the root.
What's that?
So, solitons can be created and Yeah.
Yeah.
Um
Uh
If you have a field theory, let's say
some sort of scalar field. It doesn't
matter what it is. Any kind of any kind
of set of fields.
And um
Let's suppose Okay, so here's here's
what you can do.
Let's take some lump-like
field configuration.
The field is zero everywhere is except
in some little lump region over here.
And in this lump region, and when I say
a field, it could be a set of fields. It
doesn't have to be a single field.
But, in the region over here, the field
has some
non-zero value.
Uh
And also it has a shape and a structure.
So, let's let's put some lumps blue
lumps over here.
And let's put some
black lumps on the other side.
Now, take another configuration of
exactly the same kind. Is there a
physical realization of a lump? Oh,
absolutely. There's all kinds of
physical realizations of lumps. Yeah,
nuclei are lumps.
Yeah. And in some theories nuclei
are lumps of this type.
Yeah, there's what are called skyrmion
theories of the nucleus and yeah,
there's there's there's lots and lots.
And my magnetic monopoles are like this.
Uh
And in modern quantum field theories,
almost all particles can be expressed
this way.
So, yeah, this is common.
Okay, here's another similar particle.
It's got a lump similar lump over here
and over here.
And a couple of black lumps over here
Now, I've chosen to draw two lump
configurations
which happen to be mirror images of each
other.
I can do that. I can make two mirror
images.
Call this one a particle, call this one
an antiparticle if you like. Now, start
bringing them together.
Notice that when you bring them
together, the fields will exactly match.
Why? Because the field over here is the
same as the field over here. The field
in a little bit over here is the same.
So, now imagine bringing them together.
And what happens as you bring them
together?
As you bring them together,
you can
get to a situation Where's my red pen?
You can get to a situation, for example,
you will get to a situation halfway
through
where the black lumps
have annihilated each other and the blue
lumps
are still there.
I didn't draw them very well.
And you keep squeezing it and squeezing
it and because the field always match on
the on the on the mirror,
you can just bring these field
fields together and undo them. Again,
you can see an example of this with a
belt.
Uh somebody come up and hold the other
end of the belt for me.
Okay, um
All right. You can grab it over grab it
over here.
A little closer to me.
Other hand. Oh, grab the end, too.
Be the mirror image of me, okay?
Now,
No, no, rotate. Rotate.
Right. Okay, there's a lump over here
and there's a lump at Art's end. Now,
let's push the lumps together.
I don't know if we're going to be able
to do this.
Because
Well, you can see what happens. They're
going to undo each other
because they match in the middle, all
right? So,
Grab it over here. Okay. By the time we
brought the lumps almost No, no, hold
it. Hold it. Hold it. Hold it. But, I'll
do all the twisting. There's a lump over
here and there's a lump over here. But,
if I keep pushing them together, we can
just unwind it.
That's what's going on here. This is a
three-dimensional or two-dimensional
version of the same thing.
So,
given a theory with lumps,
the lump and its mirror image can always
annihilate each other.
Okay? So, if you start with nothing,
oh, and of course you can go in the
other direction. You can take your empty
space,
um curl for lump.
Create a pair of lumps.
Right. So, you can create this pair of
lumps. You can create another pair of
lumps over here and you can rotate one
of them by 2 pi, interchange the others,
and uh
be certain
from the
topological theorem
that uh
that it's the same as doing nothing.
All right. So,
the spin-statistics theorem says that
lumps come in two types.
Those which when you rotate them, the
wave function changes sign, and those
where the wave function doesn't change
sign. Those are fermions and bosons.
Half spin
together always goes together with the
properties or the integer versus
half-integer spin always goes together
with the properties under interchange of
of the particles.
That's the theory of bosons and
fermions. The way that I heard
it described
Mhm.
was that for spin a half, if you rotate
it by 180°,
the internal spin intrinsic spin only
goes 90°.
Huh? So, if you go 2 pi, it goes to
minus one.
No. If you go to 2 pi, it goes to minus
one. Right. Yeah. And so, if you go 4
pi, Oh, no. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, no, that's exactly this that's
exactly this over here.
If you rotate by a little bit,
you pick up an e to the i theta. e to
the m theta. If m is an integer, If m is
a half, then it basically gives you a
half the phase effect. Ah, exactly.
That's right.
That's correct. And that's what
half-integer spin means.
That uh that it rotates with half the
phase, so that a full rotation doesn't
bring you back to the same thing.
Okay, question. An interesting question
is whether the
fact that when electrons are rotated by
2 pi, that the phase changes, is that
observable? Is there a way to observe
that?
And the you might think, "Well, no,
that's completely observable
unobservable because rotating rotating
by 2 pi if it only changes the sign, the
sign of a wave function doesn't matter."
But, not quite. I'm going to show you
how and this has been carried out
experimentally.
I'm going to give you a sort of purest
version of an experiment which in a
not quite pure way actually was carried
out successfully.
All right, let's start with an
experiment where you wouldn't see
anything. You would
um
you would
not see an effect.
You take an electron.
Here's the electron. It has a spin.
We're not going to worry Well, yeah,
we're going to worry Yeah, we are going
to worry about the Yeah, all right,
yeah. Here's the electron. It's going to
go through some slits.
Do some interesting interference
experiment of some kind.
It's going to go through some slits.
And before it goes into the slits from
this side over here, we're going to put
it in the cavity.
The cavity is going to have a magnetic
field. Okay?
The magnetic field What does a magnetic
field do? It latches onto the to the
spin the same way a magnetic field
latches onto
onto a compass needle.
All right, latches onto it, holds it
still.
And then we're going to take that box
and slowly rotate it by 2 pi.
And then we're going to let the electron
out of the box and create an
interference pattern over here.
We're going to compare that with the
same experiment in which instead of
slowly rotating the electron, we're not
going to slowly rotate it. That's all.
We're going to do exactly the same
experiment. In one case, a very slow
We're going to take our time. This is
going to take a long time. We're going
to take a thousand years to do this
experiment or maybe a million years.
Uh
in the first uh
um
10 to the 15 seconds or whatever it is
we'll spend setting it up
by either rotating this electron or not
rotating this electron, and then we'll
look at the interference pattern over
here.
Why is it so important to do it so
slowly?
Or why is it important to
You want to You want to
If you drag it fast, it won't hold on to
it. That's all.
Yeah.
Okay, so that's the uh that's the
experiment and the result will be that
the interference pattern in no way
remembers the uh whether it was rotated
by 2 pi.
But now we'll do a different experiment.
We'll take the electron.
And electrons are like photons. You can
You can have beam splitters.
Beam splitters will take an electron and
split the wave function of this one
electron, not two electrons.
One electron and the beam splitter uh
splits its wave function so that the
part of the wave function goes one way,
part of the wave function goes the other
way.
Again, this is not two electrons, it's
just two parts of the probability.
So, the first thing we do is we send the
electron through a beam splitter.
And two wave packets come out.
I will say over and over again, these
are not two electrons.
This is a superposition of states in
which the electron went this way
and the electron went this way.
Okay.
Now, we're going to go slow motion for a
while.
Both wave packets
are fed into a box. Into the same Into
two different boxes.
And in the box, again, there's a magnet
and a magnetic field.
Okay, so what do we have? We have a
superposition of states
in which an electron is here
an electron is here
and in this one
the electron spin
is kept parallel to a magnetic field.
And in this one, it's kept parallel to a
magnetic field.
But now I rotate one of them and not the
other. Slowly.
Okay.
Slowly until I'm finished rotating it.
One of them is rotated, the other has
not rotated.
If rotation did nothing
a rotation by 2 pi, that is. If it did
nothing
you'd say, "Well, nothing I mean, you
know, we we may have done this thing,
but nothing there's no effect of it.
This rotation by 2 pi brings it back to
the same configuration."
But no.
Rotation by 2 pi, we have a wave
function We have a wave function which
is psi
one of
x plus psi two of x.
Psi one of x is the wave function in
this box.
Psi two of x is the wave function in
this box, but after rotating
we get psi one of x minus psi two of x.
If this is the wave function that comes
out of here with a minus sign and it
passes through these two slits
the wave the uh
the uh interference pattern will be
quite different
than if you had plus.
You can see why. What will come out of
here will be a certain wave function.
What comes out of here will be a certain
wave function.
And if you add them or subtract them,
you get quite different either
destructive interference or constructive
interference.
So, this experiment
shows that under certain conditions, you
really can detect the rotation by 2 pi
by an interference experiment. Yeah. I'm
not sure what's being rotated there
since you said there's one electron
two
uh wave functions. One electron which is
in a superposition of states.
It's either in one box or in the other
box. You don't know which. And don't
look because if you look, you ruin the
experiment.
But what what When is this electron
I I I'm I'm thinking of the electron as
moving. Is it moving? No, no. You You've
captured it and uh you've captured it
for a while. You went into a box. So,
they're now cavity electrons. Yeah,
they're cavity electrons in a box. But
there's only one electron. There's only
one. It's in both cavities. No, it's
it's it's in Well,
is it in both boxes or is it in one box
or the other?
It's in a wave function which is a
superposition
of the two.
If you open the boxes and look, you will
find only one electron.
Okay?
You'll either find the electron in one
box or the other box.
If you don't And of course, if you open
the box and look, you
uh you affect the experiment in a way
which destroys any interference pattern.
The point is if you repeat this
experiment many times, you will build up
a pattern of constructive interference
or of destructive interference. Yeah,
but um you really You can really do just
one experiment.
With the minus sign here
you might get a node
in the wave function. A node means a
zero. Let's say right at the symmetry
point over here. Find out without seeing
that if the events never occur.
Let me finish. Okay.
If the wave function comes out minus,
then for sure you will not detect an
electron over here.
So, if you do detect an electron over
here, it means that there must have been
a plus sign.
So, it's it's it's it's quite
observable. This is not exactly the way
the experiment was done. I'll tell you
how the experiment was done.
The experiment was done a little bit
differently. The electron beam was split
again
and it was sent through some cylinders
with magnetic field in them along here.
Now, it was arranged so that after the
beam splitting
the electrons were polarized in a
direction perpendicular to the magnetic
field.
Do you remember what happens if an if a
if a spin is in a magnetic field
and the spin is perpendicular to the
magnetic field?
It processes.
So, if you make the cavity just exactly
long enough
and the magnetic field just right and
the velocity of the electrons correct
you can arrange so that the electron
executes one
2 pi rotation.
Uh oh, I guess in one of them
one of them you don't put the magnetic
field, I guess.
One of them you don't put the magnetic
field, the other one you do put the
magnetic field. So
one branch of the wave function
executes a 2 pi rotation, the other
branch of the wave function does not
execute a 2 pi rotation
depending on whether you turn on or not
the magnetic fields. How do you
determine
which
If you only have one electron, how do
you determine
You don't.
That's always the point of quantum
mechanics. Anything that you do to
determine the path ruins the experiment.
Uh what's your source of electron? Hm?
What you do is you go over here
and you look at the interference pattern
that happens.
What is your source of electron? What
does it look like?
A hot wire. Just a hot wire. So,
electrons are everywhere.
Yeah. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, but you can you
know, with appropriate electric and
magnetic
What's that? And you have so few
electrons, only one goes through this
side. Yeah. One one at a time. One at a
time. Absolutely.
Yeah.
So
Pardon my ignorance here, but what is it
What do you mean by
a branch of a
wave function?
Psi one plus psi two
or psi
The electron has a It has a The branch
of the wave function just means the wave
packet that goes one way or the other
way.
And so, but then it's got the same
the same um wave function?
Just
No. One of them
is non-zero here and zero here. The
other one is non-zero here and zero
here. Before it uh in the other case
over there, you're just you're just
sending electrons in and one of them is
doing something to the wave function and
the other one isn't. Yeah, but you're
you're arranging a wave function
initially
the wave function is set up by the beam
splitter
so that it is Let's call it psi one of x
plus psi two of x.
And psi one of x
is non-zero in the vicinity of this
cavity and psi two of x is non-zero in
the vicinity of this cavity.
Yes, I'm wondering how you get psi one
and psi two.
In other words, I think I've got the
electron, you've got psi. Yeah. So, is
psi one equal to psi two? Is psi one Is
psi one equal to 1/2 psi or No. No? Psi
one, for example, is some function
which looks like that.
Psi two is some function which looks
like that.
They're in different places.
Our property of what? Of the splitter.
Yeah. So, you have Okay, so you have
over here
you have electron coming in
and it hits something.
It hits something, let's say some target
over here. The target is a particular
kind of target which splits the beam
into two packets.
It splits the beam into two packet
packets. So, a wave coming in just
splits into two pieces.
They're They're charged particles, so we
can manipulate them with electric and
magnetic fields, and we take this piece
of the wave function and send it through
here, this piece of the wave function
and send it through here.
Uh
If it wasn't for these magnets, this
would just be the two-slit experiment.
So, it'd essentially be the two-slit
experiment.
It's just we have some fancy splits
fancy um slits.
The
The fancy slits are equipped with some
magnetic fields which may or may not be
turned on.
If the If the If the magnetic field is
turned on here, even though what it does
is take the the state and just rotates
it by 2 pi,
it takes you from constructive to
destructive interference over here. You
have any interference at all? I mean,
couldn't you tell which slit it came
through by seeing which tube it came
came out of?
If you look, you destroy the
interference.
interference. Anything
I'm saying afterwards, after it hits the
target.
After it hits here?
No, it just makes a It just makes a dot
there, that's all. Doesn't tell you
which uh
Let's say
you you could tell by if you took the
center point
which which one of the which one of the
two slits it is. No, you can't. No. No.
No. It spreads out Are are the tubes
after the slits or before the slits? You
better go back to the two-slit
experiment.
Go back to the two-slit experiment,
because this is exactly the same as the
two-slit experiment.
If you like,
you can think of
two-slit experiment.
You can do it for electrons and for
photons.
Wave function comes.
It either goes through this hole or this
hole, but you don't look.
And this hole you equip with a little
cylinder here, and this hole you equip
with a little cylinder.
And in one of them,
you do or you don't put a magnetic field
through it.
So, if you like, a coherent beam of
electrons comes. Coherent beam
of wave-like electrons comes.
It's just a wave.
Comes in. Some part of the wave goes
through here, some part of the wave goes
through here.
And the wave reassembles itself or it
it's
uh
we detect an electron over here.
If there's no magnetic field in the here
and here, then the wave function is
symmetric up and down, and we expect
that the that the uh that the amplitude
at the center here is going to be the
sum of the two of them,
and it's going to be particularly
large.
Um
it may be helpful. You drew the circles
on the left-hand side. If you draw the
circles on the right-hand side, you get
diffractions. So, you get circles around
each of the slits.
And then
wave going through. And then they
interfere.
Yeah. Yeah, this is
Right. This is And if they interfere
constructively, then you get this
reinforcement at the middle. Right,
that's right.
Waves go through the slits
and they spread out.
You don't know which When you get a dot
on the screen, you don't know which way
it went. No, you don't know which way it
went, but if you do know which way it
went, you destroy the interference
pattern. And that relies on the the
diameter of the tubes being
on the order of the wavelength of the
electron. The diameter of the tube has
to be on the order of the wavelength of
the electron. It has to be very
The diameter of this?
It has to be very small in order to get
the diffraction pattern.
Yeah. Yeah, this is not really the way
you would do it, but if you wanted to do
it by a conventional two-slit, yes,
you'd have to make it small. So, if if
you did this experiment with photons and
had a way to rotate them 2 pi, the two
paths would be the same. That's right.
That's right. If you did the same thing,
if you had a way
to rotate the polarization of the
photon, there's ways to do it. What
would come out here would not be
sensitive to whether to whether you
rotated by 2 pi or not. It's easier to
do with photons than than with
electrons. Probably.
Never thought about it, but uh What uh
You said there was a slight cheat in
this somewhere, right? Didn't you Didn't
you say that
they sort of cheated or something? Well,
um
The purest version of it is you want to
take that electron and very, very slowly
rotate it, so that you know that nothing
else is going on.
Here uh
it's not slow. The electron goes through
quickly, and uh
but still, it's the same phenomenon.
It's the same phenomenon.
No, it's not uh the the The slowness
just makes sure that there aren't other
things going on, jiggling in the
If it's a really long pipe, even though
the electron's moving fast, if there's a
really long pipe and a weak magnetic
field, Yeah. the rotation would be very
slow.
Okay, it's it's a legitimate It's
measuring the same effect. It's
measuring the same effect.
It's measuring the effect of uh rotation
by 2 pi on a fermion.
Right.
Um
Yeah, this is all of special case of a
phenomenon called a Berry phase.
Well, but uh
a Berry phase. It's like a strawberry
phase or a raspberry phase or a um
a Michael Berry phase.
Actually, the experiment was first
proposed by Aharonov and myself a long
time ago, but uh
Yeah. So, when the experiment was done,
was it considered a big deal or was it
like, yep, that's what we thought?
When the theory was proposed, it was
considered a big deal. Everybody By that
point, enough of these kind of things
have been done, everybody knew it would
have to work.
But
uh you know, right.
It was Yeah, it was considered
uh something surprising that people had
thought
that
under no circumstances was there any um
empirical
signature of a rotation by 2 pi. So, it
was interesting.
Yeah.
In the experiment where you have the
beam splitter, don't you have to
recombine after Yes.
Of course. Yeah.
Yeah.
Well, the wave function
the wave function
I'm not sure what recombines means. The
wave function goes through and comes out
and spreads out here.
And this one spreads out from here.
And it creates an interference pattern
by that classical uh interference uh
phenomenon. So, the slits themselves
recombine there.
What's that? The slits themselves
Yeah.
It is It It really is just a two-slit
experiment, except with an
with something inserted in near one of
the slits
to do something to the electron. And as
I said, these things are always
destroyed if there's any um you know,
little Maxwell demon watching what's
going on that records what goes on.
Yeah.
Do you happen to remember if uh you and
Aharonov thought of this idea before or
after the so-called Aharonov-Bohm
effect? Oh, it was after.
Oh, yeah. Oh, it was after, definitely.
Yeah.
1967,
I forget the Aharonov-Bohm effect was
late '50s? I can't remember. Yeah. Yeah,
a long time. Yeah.
Right.
Mhm? What is this effect?
The Aharonov-Bohm effect? It's another
funny
interference experiment.
Is it Is it the bomb bomb tester thing?
You Have you ever heard of that? There's
a sort of Oh, yeah, the
the lightning
Oh, yeah, that's it. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's a very beautiful idea.
Right.
Doesn't really have to do with bombs and
Yeah, right.
That gets your attention, though. Yeah,
it gets your attention. Right.
Okay, that's Yeah. Is it
In some sense, is this expected because
it isn't just that the probability of
not being able to combine fermions is
zero. They actually cannot be combined
into one state. It's only one fermion.
You're not combining two fermions. No, I
mean, more generally, talk about putting
two electrons into the same state, which
can't be done. Yeah, but this doesn't
have anything to do with that, because
there's only one electron. Right. Yeah.
Now, the question is, could you do the
same thing exchanging electrons? Yeah,
you could do the same thing exchanging
electrons. It's It's more complicated,
harder to visualize.
You have You start with a pair of
electrons now. Now, you literally start
with a pair of electrons.
And what you do is you Okay, let's Here
Here are some possibilities. You take
These things are wonderful. They can be
anything you want them to be.
If two electrons,
Okay?
Now, what you're going to do is you're
going to split the beam of two
electrons. That means you're going to
create a state which is a superposition
of two electrons over here
and two electrons over here. It's only
two electrons. Not No four electrons.
It's not one electron. It's not four
electrons. It's two electrons, but
either the two electrons are here
or the two electrons are here.
And now, if the two electrons are here
there's an apparatus which exchanges
them.
Somebody, you know, a field grabs onto
them and exchanges them.
If they're down here
no such thing happens.
Or perhaps we forget to switch on the
thing which uh which exchanges them.
So, the other possibility is no exchange
on either branch.
So, we split the beam of two electrons
so that we have
either two electrons here or two
electrons here. If they're here, we
exchange them. If they're here, we don't
exchange them. And then we bring them
back together again and interfere them
and see what comes out of this thing
afterwards.
Question is, do you get the same thing
or something different?
If you decide to exchange these two guys
here or if you don't.
Does the exchange, which after all does
nothing to them, right? I mean, if the
state uh doesn't care about which
electron is which.
And of course, the answer is
that uh the experiment for fermions
will detect the fact that you exchange
the two particles. The
experiment for bosons will not. Now,
what would happen? All right, here's
another experiment.
We split the pair.
Pair here or pair here.
If the pair is here
we
interchange them.
If the pair is down here, we rotate by 2
pi.
So, you would think they'd cancel.
Right.
They will.
Yeah, they will. They will cancel. The
two effects will cancel.
Right.
That uh that's the uh
Nobody's at to my knowledge nobody would
has ever done that experiment. I have a
feeling that one is uh at the moment
probably beyond the
beyond the
uh So, so does that in in any way
challenge the idea that the two
electrons are in the same physical Or
what?
No. No. Well,
it is what it is. Indistinguishable
means that if you interchange them, it
changes sign. That's what it means. Um
It means the quantum notion of
of um indistinguishable is more subtle
than the classical.
Uh
as usual.
That's the sort of thing it means,
right?
Now, of course, what's what's going on
here?
In in both of these cases, in the case
of the single electron
where you rotate one part of the world
and you don't rotate the other part.
Of course, that is not truly a rotation
by 2 pi.
A true rotation by 2 pi is the whole
world has to rotate.
If the whole world rotates, then you
don't see anything.
But all experiments that you ever do
uh compartmentalized into uh you know,
so it's it's it's it's
No, no, it it's it's still will not be
uh visible.
Yeah, so the reason this is detectable
is because you've rotated one part of
the universe relative to another.
Right. But still, you do detect the fact
that rotations by 2 pi cause a change in
sign.
So.
And that was surprising at the time.
Okay.
Hm? Yeah, it's it's it's it's surprising
today, right?
Okay, we're uh we're done for tonight.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.